<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>apolzek</title>
 <link href="https://apolzek.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://apolzek.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2026-01-27T02:41:42+00:00</updated>
 <id>https://apolzek.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>apolzek</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>How I run technical interviews</title>
   <link href="https://apolzek.github.io/2026/01/25/interview"/>
   <updated>2026-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://apolzek.github.io/2026/01/25/interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;cloud, sre, platform.. especifc context ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;grpc, http https&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aqui vai a resposta direta e estruturada para a pergunta que você pediu (como se fosse o candidato respondendo em uma entrevista técnica):a) Três diferenças fundamentais entre HTTP/1.1 e HTTP/2 que justificam a escolha obrigatória do HTTP/2 pelo gRPC:Multiplexing (fluxos múltiplos em uma única conexão TCP)
HTTP/1.1: Uma conexão TCP só permite uma requisição/resposta por vez (head-of-line blocking se houver atraso).
HTTP/2: Permite múltiplos streams independentes na mesma conexão TCP, sem bloqueio entre eles.
Binary framing + compactação de headers (HPACK)
HTTP/1.1: Protocolo textual (headers em texto plano, repetitivos).
HTTP/2: Usa frames binários + compressão de headers (HPACK), reduzindo overhead de banda e CPU.
Suporte nativo a streaming bidirecional e unidirecional
HTTP/1.1: Limitado a request-response; streaming é forçado via hacks (chunked encoding).
HTTP/2: Streams full-duplex, permitindo envio contínuo de dados em ambas as direções sem abrir novas conexões.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) Impacto prático no gRPC em cenários reais de microsserviços:Multiplexing → Permite milhares de RPCs simultâneas (unary, client streaming, server streaming, bidirectional) em uma única conexão TCP → reduz latência de setup de conexões, evita explosão de sockets e melhora throughput em alta taxa de chamadas (ex.: 10k+ RPS entre serviços).
Binary framing + HPACK → Menor payload na rede (especialmente útil com Protobuf, que já é binário e compacto) → menor latência em redes com alta latência ou baixa largura de banda; menos CPU no parsing/serialização em comparação com JSON + texto.
Streaming bidirecional → Habilita casos reais como chat em tempo real, streaming de logs/telemetria, atualizações contínuas (ex.: bidirectional streaming para ML inference ou observability push) → sem polling ou WebSocket hacks, com baixa latência e alta eficiência.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) Por que o gRPC não pode simplesmente cair para HTTP/1.1 sem perder funcionalidades críticas? Dois motivos específicos:Multiplexing e streaming bidirecional são impossíveis no HTTP/1.1 → Sem múltiplos streams na mesma conexão, bidirectional streaming (ex.: chat ou streaming de dados contínuos) quebra completamente; unary calls ficariam serializadas, causando alto tail latency e baixa throughput.
gRPC depende de trailers HTTP/2 para metadados de status e erro → O status final do RPC (OK, DEADLINE_EXCEEDED, etc.) é enviado via HTTP/2 trailers (após o body). HTTP/1.1 não tem trailers equivalentes de forma nativa e confiável → perda de informações críticas de erro/status, quebrando a semântica do RPC.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Proposing a workflow for tracking and maintaining complex architectures</title>
   <link href="https://apolzek.github.io/2026/01/20/proposing-a-workflow"/>
   <updated>2026-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://apolzek.github.io/2026/01/20/proposing-a-workflow</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You are an &lt;strong&gt;SRE&lt;/strong&gt; and you like having a holistic view of the product. Or maybe you are a &lt;strong&gt;Platform Engineer&lt;/strong&gt; and want to understand every part of the platform and how data flows through it. The problem is that the team does not have this view. Most of the knowledge lives in the heads of the most senior people. The decision-making context stayed with them. What you are left with is an outdated inventory and, if you are lucky, a few partially documented flows :&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when you roll up your sleeves and start doing reverse engineering of the product or platform. Time to “&lt;strong&gt;Give it everything you’ve got&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, you start somewhere. You map connections, figure out which server talks to which one, where the databases are, how read and write flows work. What runs on Kubernetes, what is still on VM or Bare metal. A hybrid environment, with cloud mixed in. Even with sophisticated tools, the environment is complex. At some point, you have to go all the way down to the network packet level and run tcpdump without mercy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long journey, you finally get an updated architecture diagram. &lt;em&gt;Servers, services, ports, external components&lt;/em&gt;, everything in one place. A map that actually makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you do after that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you understand the end-to-end flows. Just like a doctor blinks and “sees” human anatomy, you blink and see the &lt;strong&gt;entire system/platform&lt;/strong&gt;. As Uncle Ben said, &lt;em&gt;“ßwith great power comes great responsibility”&lt;/em&gt;. Your role now is to help less senior people reach the same level of understanding. The people who support the system also need this view, so they can break out of the endless loop of repetitive on-call actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where you start thinking about how to make this knowledge fluid, accessible, and evolvable. And this is exactly where the workflow I have been enjoying comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[WARN] Nothing I am proposing here is new. All of this already exists and works well. If there is any merit here, it is probably just about connecting the dots. “&lt;em&gt;Connect the dots&lt;/em&gt;,” as Steve Jobs once said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is simple: once you finish the architecture drawing, translate it into Mermaid, following some standards. You can define your own, but here are the steps I usually follow. From a napkin sketch to Mermaid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add all components, organized into groups and subgroups&lt;/strong&gt;. VMs are not Kubernetes, so they should be &lt;strong&gt;separate groups&lt;/strong&gt;. Each has its own characteristics, and that should be explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add the arrows connecting components&lt;/strong&gt;, but always think in terms of flows. &lt;em&gt;Read vs write flows, primary vs secondary, user vs system&lt;/em&gt;. Mermaid supports &lt;em&gt;styling&lt;/em&gt;, so take advantage of that. Use different arrow styles, annotations on components, or notes directly on the arrows. Something like a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#cash-in&lt;/code&gt; tag already adds useful context.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you define a visual standard, document it. &lt;strong&gt;Create a separate Mermaid diagram that acts as a legend&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the “&lt;em&gt;how to work with this diagram&lt;/em&gt;” guide. Everyone on the team should &lt;em&gt;follow it&lt;/em&gt;. You do not want to be the owner of this diagram. Trust me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the flow documented, it is time to work on top of it. &lt;strong&gt;Create a page for ADRs&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Architecture Decision Records&lt;/em&gt;). For each proposed change, document the change itself, the context, the options (P1, P2, P3), what is expected from each, and whether it was accepted or not. If it was accepted, state which one. Depending on the company, this will turn into a GMUD or an RFC, the formal change document.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you schedule a meeting to discuss the change, if it makes sense, open the &lt;strong&gt;Mermaid diagram in Excalidraw&lt;/strong&gt;. It supports Mermaid natively. Import the diagram without worrying about styles. This is where the team &lt;em&gt;discusses solutions, scribbles, connects and disconnects arrows, and explores possibilities freely&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the change is approved, &lt;strong&gt;execute the GMUD or RFC&lt;/strong&gt;. Do it with a clear plan: &lt;em&gt;post-execution tests, a rollback plan, notification plan, documented monitoring, and properly tuned alerts&lt;/em&gt;. No production heroics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If everything goes well, update the status of the GMUD, RFC, and the ADR to “accepted,” clearly stating which solution was chosen, especially if there were multiple options.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update the official Mermaid diagram&lt;/strong&gt; with all the changes that came out of the Excalidraw session. Add context and notify the team and stakeholders about the change(post change).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To wrap up&lt;/em&gt;..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you’ve put in all the work to &lt;strong&gt;standardize things&lt;/strong&gt;, it’s time to reap the benefits. Your arrows have styles or tags, so you can probably already see where this is going. From here on, this becomes a perfect playground for using &lt;strong&gt;LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;. You can use them not just to sketch things out for you, but also to help you understand your architecture and even give feedback on it. You can ask them to isolate flows, like “&lt;em&gt;isolate the flow with red arrows,&lt;/em&gt;” or “&lt;em&gt;isolate components with a specific tag, like #cash-in”. You can also ask questions such as “&lt;/em&gt;what are the weak points in my architecture* ?? “.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few ideas, but once your diagrams are structured, the kinds of questions you can ask and the insights you can get grow really fast. **After all that, make some coffee and go listen to good music. 🤠&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mermaid legend&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-mermaid&quot;&gt;flowchart LR
    A --&amp;gt; B
    B --&amp;gt; C
    C --&amp;gt; D
    D --&amp;gt; E

    %% Todos os links da mesma cor/espessura
    linkStyle default stroke:#ff4444,stroke-width:3px

    %% Só links específicos (começa do 0 na ordem que aparecem)
    linkStyle 0 stroke:#00cc00,stroke-width:5px
    linkStyle 2 stroke:blue,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>apolzek</title>
   <link href="https://apolzek.github.io/2026/01/16/apolzek"/>
   <updated>2026-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://apolzek.github.io/2026/01/16/apolzek</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Júlio&lt;/strong&gt;, from &lt;em&gt;Cocoricó&lt;/em&gt;, is the pure embodiment of a curious boy. He lives on a farm, but his mind is always wandering: he asks questions, imagines possibilities, tests slightly crazy hypotheses, and learns along the way. His curiosity isn’t just about knowing “what something is,” but “why it is that way” and “what if it were different.” This often puts him in confusing situations, but it is also the driving force behind all his discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Júlio, I am trying to return to the purity of my being and relearn how to learn. This blog is a mixture of technical topics, philosophical reflections, personal confessions, and worldviews. Here, I write primarily for myself, with the intention of being honest rather than performing for the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people use a nickname to hide behind a character. To me, our given name is already a projection of the person we pretend to be. We naturally create a social mask to navigate the world and interact with others. That’s why &lt;strong&gt;apolzek&lt;/strong&gt; is where I place my essence and express my true identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve stumbled upon this, welcome aboard! When you read any post here, know that you’ll be behind the scenes of my mind. Let’s go together, let’s go with &lt;strong&gt;God&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
Daughter, 2025 Jan 15 you were extubated at Vila da Serra Hospital. I am so happy that it creates indescribable reactions in me. I love you, I love our family, I love life, I love God.
--&gt;

&lt;!-- 
My birth name, Vinícius Gomes Batista, is the name I was given when I was presented to God and welcomed into this life. It holds my story, my family roots, and a sense of purpose. Over the years, though, that name has picked up so many layers. Social expectations, roles I learned to play, ways I adapted to fit in. Most of the time those things don’t feel like the real me at my deepest level. That’s why I created apolzek. It’s not about replacing Vinícius or turning my back on him. It’s more like a deliberate practice, almost a quiet sacred space, where I try to bring the real Vinícius closer to who he truly is underneath everything. When I’m in apolzek mode, I focus on stripping away those extra layers. I try to speak and act with complete honesty toward myself, and I refuse to let the outside world tell me who I’m supposed to be. In those moments it’s just me, no masks, standing in front of God.
--&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
